<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  Copyright [2010], Red Hat, Inc., and individual contributors
  by the @authors tag. See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  full listing of individual contributors.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="exception.handling.client_usage">
   <title>Usage</title>
   <para>
      An end user of the Seam Catch Framework is typically only concerned with Exception Handlers (methods in Handler
      Beans, which are similar to CDI Observers). Handler Beans are CDI beans with the
      <literal>@HandlesExceptions</literal>
      annotation. There may be other resources made available by other modules
      which can be injected into handler methods on an as needed basis. For further information, please check the API
      docs, or examples.
   </para>

   <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.annotations">
      <title>Annotations</title>

      <section>
         <title>@HandlesExceptions</title>

         <para>
            The
            <literal>@HandlesException</literal>
            annotation is simply a marker annotation instructing the Seam
            Catch CDI extension to scan the bean for handler methods.
         </para>

         <para>
            Example
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@HandlesExceptions
public class MyHandlers
{
    public void catchAllHandler(@Handles(during = TraversalPath.DESCENDING) @MyFramework CaughtException<Throwable> event, Logger log)
    {
        log.warn("Exception occured: " + event.getException().getMessage());
    }
}]]>
         </programlisting>

         <para>
            This is a complete and valid handler showing all the current features of handlers. The Handler Bean is
            defined by the class level annotation
            <literal>@HandlesExceptions</literal>
            and the actual handler is
            defined by the method that takes a
            <literal>CaughtException</literal>
            of type
            <literal>Throwable</literal>
            which is annotated using the
            <literal>@Handles</literal>
            annotation. Also notice the handler is qualified
            using the
            <literal>@MyFramework</literal>
            qualifier. This works the same as qualifers in CDI Observers,
            it will only be invoked for exceptions (it catches type<literal>Throwable</literal>) where the initial
            <literal>ExceptionToCatchEvent</literal>
            was created with the
            <literal>@MyFramework</literal>
            annotation passed to the constructor. The Logger instance is also injected into the handler when it is
            invoked. The handler has a default precedence of 0 and a
            <literal>TraversalPath</literal>
            of
            <literal>DESCENDING</literal>. It does not modify flow control of other handlers however and simply uses
            the default proceed.
         </para>

         <note>This annotation may be deprecated favoring annotation indexing done by Seam Solder.</note>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>@Handles</title>

         <para>
            <literal>@Handles</literal>
            is a parameter annotation that specifies a method as an exception handler. It
            acts similar to the
            <literal>@Observes</literal>
            annotation from CDI. In addition to promoting a normal
            method to an exception handler it also carries data about the handler:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>a precedence relative to other handlers of the same type (the heigher the precendence, the
               closer to the top of the causing traversal it is placed, relative to other handlers for the same
               exception type, zero being the default)
            </listitem>
            <listitem>the direction of the traversal path during which the handler is invoked
               (
               <literal>TraversalPath.ASCENDING</literal>
               being default)
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            The
            <literal>@Handles</literal>
            annotation must be placed on the first parameter of the method, which must be of type CaughtException.
            Handler methods are similar to CDI Obeservers and follow the same principals and guidelines (such as
            invocation, injection of parameters, qualifiers, etc). They differ from Observer methods in that:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>they are ordered before they are invoked</listitem>
            <listitem>the first parameter of the method must be a generized CaughtException object</listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            A handler is guaranteed to only be invoked once per exception (unless it is unmuted via the CaughtException
            object by calling<literal>unMute()</literal>). Handlers must not throw checked exceptions, and should
            avoid throwing unchecked exceptions.
         </para>
      </section>

   </section>

   <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.adding_handlers">
      <title>Adding Handlers</title>
      <para>
         Adding a handler is simply creating a class and a method the follows the above rules (class annotated with
         <literal>@HandlesExceptions</literal>
         and a method with the first parameter being a CaughtException and annotated
         with<literal>@Handles</literal>). Catch will discover all handler methods at deploy time. See the example
         above for a simple, but complete handler.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.ordering_handlers">
      <title>Ordering of Handlers</title>
      <para>
         The ordering of handlers is multifaceted. Based on the traversal path of the causing container handlers are
         ordered according to the hiearchy of the excption type (most specific first if
         <literal>TraversalPath.ASCENDING</literal>, least specific first if
         <literal>TraversalPath.DESCENDING</literal>
         traversal), and the precedence when two handlers are for the
         same exception type.
      </para>
      <para>
         The
         <literal>precedence</literal>
         of a handler helps determine the order of the handler relative to other
         handlers of the same exception type. It follows a high-to-low integer schema (the higher the precedence, the
         sooner the handler is invoked during traversal of the causing chain).
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.traversal">
      <title>Traversal of the causing container</title>

      <para>
         When an exception is handled with Catch the causing container is unwrapped to get at each exception. The
         first pass (<literal>TraversalPath.DESCENDING</literal>) starts with the outer most exception working it's
         way to the root exception. The traversal is then reversed and traversed from root cause up. This allows
         handlers to take part in various stages of the causing container. At each entry in the container, handlers
         are invoked based on the exception type (either an exact match or a super type) of the entry. For example
         if the exception type is<literal>SocketException</literal>, handlers for types
         <literal>SocketException</literal>,
         <literal>IOException,</literal>
         <literal>Exception</literal>
         and
         <literal>Throwable</literal>
         would all invoked (in that order), however, a handler for
         <literal>BindException</literal>
         would not be invoked.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.api">
      <title>API Objects</title>

      <para>
         There are other objects used in Catch that should be familiar to handler writers namely
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <literal>CaughtException</literal>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <literal>ExceptionStack</literal>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.api.catchevent">
         <title>CaughtException</title>

         <para>
            <literal>CaughtException</literal>
            contains methods to interact with the handling procces, allowing a
            level of flow control to be available to handler (such as re-throwing the exception, or aborting), and
            allowing a handler to be unmuted. Once a handler is invoked it is muted, meaning it will not be run again
            for that causing container, unless it is explicitly marked as unmuted via the
            <literal>CaughtException.unMute()</literal>
            object.
         </para>

         <para>
            Five methods exist on the
            <literal>CaughtException</literal>
            object to give flow control to the handler
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <literal>abort()</literal>
               - terminate all handling immediately after this handler, does not mark the
               exception as handled, does not re-throw the exception.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <literal>rethrow()</literal>
               - continues through all handlers, but once all handlers have been called
               (assuming another handler does not call abort() or handled()) the initial exception passed to Catch is
               rethrown. Does not mark the exception as handled.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <literal>handled()</literal>
               - marks the exception as handled and terminates further handling.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <literal>proceed()</literal>
               - default. Marks the exception as handled and proceeds with the rest of the
               handlers.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <literal>proceedToCause()</literal>
               - marks the exception as handled, but proceeds to the next cause in
               the cause container, without calling other handlers for the current cause.
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="exception.handling.client_usage.api.stackinfo">
         <title>ExceptionStack</title>

         <para>
            <literal>ExceptionStack</literal>
            contains information about the cause container relative to the current
            cause. Please see API docs for more information, all methods are fairly self-explanatory.
         </para>
      </section>

   </section>

   <!--
   vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
   -->
</chapter>
